<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Monarchia microcosmi the origin, vicissitudes, and period of vital government in man : for a farther discovery of diseases, incident to human nature / by Everard Maynwaringe ...</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19619</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12351229</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12351229</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60019</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 642:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Monarchia microcosmi the origin, vicissitudes, and period of vital government in man : for a farther discovery of diseases, incident to human nature / by Everard Maynwaringe ...</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 57, [1], 52, [2], 39, [1], 20, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Everingham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 57.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: "Inquiries into the general catalogue of diseases", "The practice of physick reformed", and "A brief account of the catholick medicine", all with caption titles, are lacking in filmed copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60019:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60019:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Monarchia Microcoſmi:</hi> THE Origin, Viciſſitudes, and Period OF VITAL GOVERNMENT IN MAN.</p>
            <p>For a farther Diſcovery of Diſeaſes, incident to Human Nature.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Everard Maynwaringe,</hi> M. D.</p>
            <p>Licens'd and Enter'd according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Everingham</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> near the Weſt End of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60019:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60019:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Monarchia Microcoſmi.</hi> THE Origin, Viciſſitudes, and Period of Vital Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in MAN.</head>
            <p>POlitical Governments, their Riſe, Laws, Innovations and Revolutions, Subjected to the Will of Men; are not my buſineſs to treat of: But the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> eſtabliſhed in Man; by the Laws of <hi>Nature;</hi> not liable to human Subverſion; is the great Concern of every Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian; as the Baſis of his Knowledge, and the Subject of Medical Art.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60019:3"/>
            <p>For a right underſtanding of this Government; we muſt divide Man into his two principal Parts; the <hi>Governing,</hi> and the <hi>Governed.</hi> The governing power; is <hi>ſpiritual, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> and <hi>inviſible,</hi> termed the Soul. The governed, is <hi>corporal, organic,</hi> and <hi>inſtrumental,</hi> called the Body. Deficiency or failure in either of theſe two principal Parts, makes a Diſeaſed and infirm State of Man: And that you may the better know where to charge the Defections that ariſe from human Nature; theſe two grand Parts are duly to be inquired into: Firſt <hi>(Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim)</hi> in their ſingle and different Natures; Secondly <hi>(Conjunctim)</hi> as they are yoaked in Partnerſhip, which compoſe and denominate Man.</p>
            <p>The Magiſterial and Governing Power, being the ſuperior and more noble Part, ruling the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine</hi> or Body of Man; is firſt to be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60019:3"/>conſidered: And now we muſt look back into the Book of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to trace the <hi>Origin</hi> of this Governing Principle; which I find, began in <hi>Adam;</hi> whoſe Soul took its Riſe immediatly from the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Creator: The Manner how; the Matter what, or no matter; the integrity and purity of that created vital Principle, are <hi>Theologick</hi> Queſtions, and out of my Province, which I paſs over.</p>
            <p>But in the beginning of <hi>Time;</hi> after the Creation was <hi>finiſhed,</hi> and the courſe of Nature <hi>Eſtabliſhed;</hi> when all things ſprung by <hi>Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and owned a traductive <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> from the Womb of Nature; and time appointed, to prefix, and meaſure out their Durations: Then I ſay, and now; the propagation and production of Souls, are a Philoſophical and Phyſical Subject; ſo neceſſary to be inquired, and well known by a Phyſician; that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60019:4"/>without ſuch Knowledge, he is abſurdly deficient, in the grand Fundamental of Human Nature; whereon mainly reſts the whole <hi>Fabrick</hi> of Phyſick, as hereafter will appear.</p>
            <p>The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> being compleated, and furniſhed with its Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Animals;</hi> Creation then ceaſed: But for the Continuation of all theſe wonderful Productions, until the <hi>Exit</hi> and <hi>Period</hi> of Time; there was a Power delegated to Nature, by the <hi>Conditor Mundi,</hi> and Commiſſions given to all the <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> of Creatures for Propagation.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Creſcite &amp; multiplicamini;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Increaſe and multiply.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Now what is there here below, that ſprings not out of Nature, (immediate) as the Product of that fertile omniferous Creature (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) pregnant with innumerable kinds of Animals? <hi>(Sic tulit ordinatio divina)</hi> Since this is the Reſult of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60019:4"/>divine Will, and command of Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency, expreſly: Nor is it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating from human rational Soul, to be derived by Generation, from the firſt Parents; but moſt reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as moſt evident; bearing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the Characters of the <hi>Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſt,</hi> in his lapſed nature. But the general current and crowd of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, runs very ſtrongly againſt the procreation of Souls: therefore I muſt not paſs it by ſlightly, but make a farther Proof of this grand Point.</p>
            <p>That the firſt Man <hi>Adam,</hi> had his Soul by Creation; I think no Body doubts; But his Poſterity, (if we be his Poſterity;) muſt derive from him a Rational Soul; <hi>(omnis forma eſt ſuî multiplicativa)</hi> or elſe we cannot be truly ſaid to be deſcended from him; and that we are deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from his lapſed Nature, and do participate thereof; our <hi>frailties</hi> and <hi>mortality,</hi> are Arguments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60019:5"/>
            <p>What can we claim from <hi>Adam,</hi> if the Soul be not <hi>propagated</hi> and derived from him? The viſible cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal matter, of which human Bodies are compoſed, is ſuch, and from ſuch matter, as we eat and drink daily. <hi>Ex iis nutrimur, ex quibus conſtamus.</hi> What is <hi>Genital Spermatick</hi> Matter? but an Elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated <hi>Succus,</hi> extracted daily from our Food; which receiving ſeveral alterations in paſſing through the Body; at laſt arriving at the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Parts; there take a <hi>Spermatick</hi> digeſtion and tranſmutation; and this is the <hi>(materia ex qua)</hi> viſible and only matter, of which all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated Human Bodieies are made. Now what relation hath this <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migenious</hi> matter to <hi>Adam?</hi> Truly none; for this we muſt own to have from the Fleſh of <hi>Beaſts, Fiſh, Fowl,</hi> and all ſorts of Food. And how is the <hi>Embryo</hi> in the Womb, nouriſhed and improved? but with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60019:5"/>alimentary juice, of the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction: And after the Birth; Augmentation is procured, by dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly additions of Aliment, to the ſtate and full growth; which Bulk is maintained afterwards by ſupplies of the ſame kind. 'Tis plain and undeniable then; that the <hi>Corporal.</hi> Subſtance of our Bodies, are wholly derived from, and made up of the matter of our Food: Then it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follows; we can no way claim Kindred to <hi>Adam;</hi> but only by deriving the better, and more noble part from him, which is the Rational Soul; by which the whole <hi>Race</hi> of Mankind, may truly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Adamites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay <hi>(homo generat hominem)</hi> Man begets Man; and ſo ſay I, the whole Man: But you underſtand and mean thereby; that Man begets only a <hi>Senſitive</hi> Soul; and and the <hi>Rational</hi> to be infuſed by Creation: What then is the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60019:6"/>and unavoidable Conſequence? <hi>Homo non generat hominem, ſolum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo brutam:</hi> Man begets a Brute only. If your Theology and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy do thus interfere and claſh, how will you reconcile them?</p>
            <p>But now you tell me of a <hi>ſenſitive</hi> and <hi>brutal</hi> Soul in Man; gives me oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to inquire, into the Doctrine, <hi>(trium Animarum)</hi> of three Souls in Man; Vegetative, Senſitive, and Rational; confirmed by a general Vogue; as alſo by the Decree of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Phyloſophers and Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, ancient and modern. True it is; there are three diſtinct and different Souls in <hi>rerum natura;</hi> but I think not ſo, in <hi>humana natura;</hi> ſince one is ſufficient to perform all Functions in Human Nature. But to offer any Argument againſt ſuch a <hi>Sanction;</hi> you will ſay is a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Attempt: Notwithſtanding, I muſt inquire into the Verity of this Judgment; for as much as,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60019:6"/>the Doctrine is <hi>Fundamental,</hi> and the Dependants thereupon, are of great Conſequence in Phyſick; ſince the Deſigns of Curing cannot be well grounded, without a true knowledge of the <hi>Governing</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; from whence principally and moſt frequently, <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> do ariſe and depend.</p>
            <p>If there be three Souls in Man, we are induſtriouſly to inquire their Properties, Powers, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions; that upon failure in this or that Part of the Body; any <hi>Function</hi> or <hi>Office</hi> not duly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we may then know upon which Governing Principle to charge the Deficiency, and in what <hi>Organ</hi> the Impediment lies. Every Soul muſt have its Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and where any failure is found, we may then know under what <hi>Governing</hi> Power, that Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Part of the Body is Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected: whether a Failure in <hi>Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60019:7"/>Senſation,</hi> or <hi>Intellection:</hi> In all which, rightly diſtinguiſhing the Deficiency of the <hi>Vital</hi> Powers; from the decays of the <hi>Inſtrumental</hi> Parts. And here by the way; you may take notice, how Diſeaſes do ariſe; either by the declenſion or ſwerving of the Vital <hi>Governing</hi> Principle; or from the impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and incapacity of the <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> Organs for Action: And by this Knowledge or Proſpect, the Deſigns of Curing are radically in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and performed; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, all Endeavours for reducing of Diſeaſes, are but caſual Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and groaping in the dark.</p>
            <p>The three denominating, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, and regent Principles, or Powers; <hi>Vegetative, Senſitive,</hi> and <hi>Rational,</hi> make the three grand <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerical</hi> Diviſions of Animate Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; which laſt, being the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtep in the Scale of Nature (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing <hi>Virtualiter</hi> the two inferior)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60019:7"/>denominates and conſtitutes <hi>Man;</hi> whereby he is elevated to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Perfection and Dignity, above all Creatures in the lower World. But if there be a <hi>Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,</hi> and <hi>Senſient</hi> Soul in Man, as diſtinct and ſeparate Principles; then I <hi>quaere</hi> what ſort of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment this is in the <hi>Microcoſm,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three principal Rulers; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther each of them exerciſeth Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination independently, and hath their Territories ſo diſtinct; not accountable to the other, and are as three <hi>Monarchs?</hi> or whether the two inferior in Dignity, do act ſubordinately by Deputation as <hi>Vice Roys</hi> or <hi>Provincials? Ruling</hi> Powers, are <hi>real</hi> Powers; elſe you give Titles and Names to things without a Being. Or thirdly; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Ruling Powers are Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate and Coequal, and do make a <hi>State</hi> Government? But I ſhall not proſecute upon theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60019:8"/>they having no foundation in Human Nature, which I ſhall endeavour to prove. And now I am forced to ſearch the <hi>Records</hi> of Sacred Writ, for we can have no account but from thence; elſe I am unwilling to be an Interpreter of Scripture, ſave only for my own ſatisfaction; wherein I had rather follow, than lead.</p>
            <p>If there be three Souls in Man; they were all <hi>created</hi> in <hi>Adam;</hi> or ſome of them <hi>procreated</hi> afterwards in his Poſterity. Not created in him; for the Greek Text ſays; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Latin thus; <hi>Et factus eſt homo in Animam Viventem:</hi> The Engliſh Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>And Man became a living Soul:</hi> All run in the ſingular number, a Soul: And to add any other to his Nature of an inferior rank, a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, brutal, and mortal Soul; is to change that Integrity, Purity, and Immortality, in which he was created.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60019:8"/>
            <p>Nor do we read (in Sacred Writ) of any <hi>addition</hi> to his created Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, after the Fall; but of <hi>diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, depravation,</hi> and loſs of what he had; but no <hi>new</hi> Principle ſuperad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, no <hi>ſenſitive</hi> brutal Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Formavit Dominus Deus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem de limo terrae, &amp; inſpiravit in faciem ejus ſpiraculum vitae,—Gen. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 7. The ſtupendious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin of Man's Body, with all its variety of Organs, was firſt fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before the Breath of Life was infuſed; which Breath, was the laſt act to conſtitute and compleat the firſt Man: but as for the <hi>manner</hi> how; expreſſed by Breathing in; or the <hi>matter</hi> what; or no <hi>matter;</hi> is not my buſineſs to inquire after; only the Simplicity, Unity, and Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, of that created Vital Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, is here ſought for, and ſet forth: And that all <hi>vital</hi> Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Body, might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by one active <hi>vital</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60019:9"/>a wonderful Agent, inſpired, by the omnipotent worker of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; is as intelligible, probable, and more rational; than that they ſhould proceed from 3 or 2 diſtinct Principles of Vitality: Therefore a <hi>trinity</hi> or <hi>duality</hi> of Souls, in created Human Nature, is not reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with Reaſon; ſince we do not find it ſo expreſſed, in the Hiſtory of the Creation, nor any neceſſity to allow it. <hi>Entia non ſunt multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicanda ſine neceſſitate.</hi> Tell me what this <hi>ſenſitive</hi> or <hi>brutal</hi> Soul is; when, and how introduced into Human Body; created or genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>Et eris mihi magnus Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Philoſophers and Phyſitians cannot agree, what this <hi>Anima ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiva</hi> is. Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> will have the Animal Spirits to be the ſenſitive Soul. <hi>Profectò (quicquid alii ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerint) Spiritus Animales revera exiſtere, ipſiuſque Animae corporeae hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſin conſtituere;—in Praefat. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60019:9"/>cerebri:</hi> But although this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, lays ſuch a ſtreſs upon <hi>Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal</hi> Spirits, as to make them ſuch a conſiderable Principle; yet ſome doubt, whether there be <hi>Animal</hi> Spirits diſtinct from the Vital; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers flatly deny them: Men very eminent in this Faculty.</p>
            <p>The learned Dr. <hi>Charlton</hi> ſo du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitats upon Animal Spirits, as to my thinking, inſinuates a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. (6th Praelection of Human Nature:) The famous <hi>Harvey (de generat. Animal. exercit.</hi> 70.) plainly denys their exiſtence. Alſo, Sir <hi>George Ent Antidiatrib.</hi> p. 141.) likewiſe <hi>Scaliger,</hi> (<hi>exercit.</hi> 339. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.) And moſt of the Peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticks, are of the ſame opinion. Notwithſtanding upon this imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Foundation of <hi>Animal</hi> Spirits, that Doctor raiſeth his <hi>Anima Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiva;</hi> and his Doctrine of <hi>Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> Motions, and Epileptick Inſults, is planted thereupon. Dr. <hi>Willis, de
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60019:10"/>Morbis Convulſivis.</hi> But admitting the exiſtence of <hi>Animal</hi> Spirits, yet they being but meer Inſtruments; how is it rational they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute an independent <hi>Principle,</hi> and be the Author of ſuch great Actions, as are attributed to a <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive</hi> Soul.</p>
            <p>From the firſt Man created; we will ſtep over to his Poſterity gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; and ſee if we can find a <hi>plurality</hi> of Souls, in Human pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Nature. <hi>Adam begat a Son in his own likeneſs, after his image, and called his name Seth,</hi> Gen. 5. v. 3. not a likeneſs in <hi>Shape</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi> only; but a likeneſs in his <hi>ſpecifick</hi> Human Nature, compounded of Soul and Body; a Man. And if <hi>Seth</hi> was <hi>Adam</hi>'s likeneſs; he muſt have but one Soul, as his Father had no more: elſe the diſſimilitude between <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son,</hi> would be great and monſtrous; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the general Rule: <hi>Quicquid
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60019:10"/>est in effectu, praeexiſtit in cauſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Seth</hi> being the firſt-born; in him began the courſe of Human Nature by <hi>Propagation;</hi> anſwering the general Inſtitution by Divine Will, declared to all Animate Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; <hi>Increaſe and repleniſh the Earth:</hi> Man not excepted in this general Command: An Argument ſufficient to ſilence all reaſoning, and farther diſquiſition.</p>
            <p>But the adverſe Party, holding the <hi>daily</hi> creation of Souls; and yet to derive the Generations after <hi>Adam,</hi> from his <hi>humane nature;</hi> have framed this Invention; that the Seed of Parents contains a <hi>Plaſtic</hi> or formative Power, as an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment endowed with Virtue from the <hi>Generants,</hi> to form and orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the <hi>Foetus</hi> in the Womb; which Body being compleated; the Rational Soul is then infuſed by Creation after this manner: <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur infundendo; creando infunditur.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60019:11"/>Thus ſuppoſing the traductive ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating Power of Parents is maintained in <hi>Semine,</hi> by an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of the generating Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, to perform in its ſtead, and abſence. All which in my reaſon is very abſurd; <hi>Tum daretur acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ſine ſubſtantia &amp; ſubjecto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, there is a (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) forming Power, or formative Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in <hi>Semine;</hi> but this always preſuppoſeth a formative Principle, from whence this Virtue does iſſue, and is dependent upon; never act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its abſence. <hi>(Actio fieri non poteſt ab inſtrumentis, ſine opifice)</hi> This <hi>Plaſtic</hi> Power being inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable from the <hi>Plaſtic</hi> Principle, <hi>Anima:</hi> Can you ſeparate <hi>Light</hi> from the Sun, or <hi>Heat</hi> from Fire; or <hi>Humidity</hi> from Water? no more can you imagin, (rationally and really) a <hi>Plaſtic</hi> emaning Virtue, without a <hi>Plaſtic</hi> Principle. <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens non migrat, de ſubjecto in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectum.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60019:11"/>For, <hi>Semen inanimatum eſt in faecundum omnino.</hi> Can any natural Agent contrive and fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate a Manſion ſo appoſite and fit in all its Organs, as the Soul it ſelf; whereby to exert all its vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Endowments, and to perform all its different Offices; carrying the Idea of it ſelf, for the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its ſpecifick Likeneſs; which no vicarious Inſtrument or Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, can perform in his abſence. Look through the Univerſe, among all the Species of Creatures, and you will not find any formative and productive Power, delegated to perform the Office of the ſpecifick generating Principle. And why in the formation of Man, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Soul, ſhould be denied and debarred the formative Power acting preſentially; is to my think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, no way conſonant with Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as being againſt the Rules of Philoſophy; which do not run
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60019:12"/>counter to Theology; both being rightly underſtood; as proceeding from Divine will and appointment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anima ex traduce,</hi> is not my ſingle Opinion; but ſome eminent Divines and Philoſophers have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the ſame; and therefore I am not a leader, but a follower herein: only ſet forth ſomething differently to give light to ſome Truths of great moment in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. But continued Creation is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately defended, to ſupport the immortality of Human Soul, and therefore they cannot admit of its Generation by mortal Man: And according to the Axiom in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy; <hi>Quod eſt generabile eſt etiam corruptibile;</hi> which ſeems to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe and thwart an Article of our Faith: Yet rightly underſtood, it does not; but conſonant with the Analogy of Faith, and Tenor of Divine Oracles; that <hi>This corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible</hi> (Body) <hi>ſhall put on incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60019:12"/>and This mortal</hi> (Soul) <hi>ſhall put on immortality:</hi> not in this Life, but in that which is to come; when mortal Life is ended. (<hi>Anima quae peccaverit, ipſa morietur.</hi> So that notwithſtanding, Mortality follows Generation; Reſurrection and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Immortality, are as certain as ſacred Writ hath made them; and no alteration, or injury offered to our Creed. Much more there is to be ſaid; but I forbear, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be an interpreter of Scripture: But the Subject of our Diſcourſe, unavoidably engaged me herein: I only offer ſo much, to ſhew the innocency of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; no way favouring of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, or Fanaticiſm: <hi>Salvâ fide Chriſtiana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anima vivicans,</hi> the Vital Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and <hi>forma informans:</hi> This is the <hi>Spiritus Architectonicus;</hi> here is this <hi>vis plaſtica;</hi> the formative Power emerging from the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60019:13"/>Principle: This is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>calidum innatum;</hi> (much talk'd of; but not underſtood) the Fountain of all Vital Heat: This is <hi>Anima Vegetativa;</hi> the Author of all acts of Vegetation in Human Bodies: And this is the <hi>Anima Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiva;</hi> the Spring of Senſation, and <hi>loco motion.</hi> All theſe Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties emaning from one and the ſame Principle of Life; and are not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral and different Principles in themſelves. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicus tantum eſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae moderator, nec plures.</hi> Human Soul having a triple Specifick En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telechia, compriſed in one Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the Epitome of all Animat Creatures; and governs the little World of Man, by a <hi>Monarchical</hi> Power: Ruling the upper, middle, and lower Regions thereof, with their Confines: And to admit of any other Animat Principle, as ſharing in this Government; were a diminution of the <hi>Royalty,</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60019:13"/>a leſsning of the <hi>Prerogative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt here infert the words of a learned <hi>Author,</hi> pertinent to the purpoſe; which wraps up our mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into one bundle: <hi>Anima dum Vivificat corpus, Anima eſt; dum Vult, Anionus; dum Scit Mens; dum Recolit, Memoria; dum rectum Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat, Ratio; dum ſpirat, Spiritus; dum aliquid Sentit, Senſus eſt.</hi> Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus. So that all theſe different Appellations, which have amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the World; do ſignifie and diſtinguiſh various Operations on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; proceeding from one, and the ſame Principle, performing divers Offices belonging to Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Anima quippe officia cuncta partibus diſtribuit, eaque per vitam moderatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay; <hi>cui bono?</hi> What ſignifies all this to Phyſician and Patient, whoſe Concern is Bodily Curing; that of <hi>Souls</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Divines only. To which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60019:14"/>I anſwer; you are under a great miſtake: <hi>Cadaver non capax est Morborum:</hi> The Body abſtractly conſidered, is not capable of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; but <hi>Corpus vivens;</hi> nor is the Body capable of Curing, but by the Power of the Vital Principle, <hi>Animae:</hi> for as <hi>Helmont</hi> ſays; <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura eſt Morborum Medicatrix:</hi> By Nature is underſtood the Life, or Principle of Life, which you call the Soul. What is a Diſeaſe, but a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or impediment in Vital Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And this ariſeth from Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity or Defection of the Vital Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; or decay and alteration of the corporeal inſtrumental Parts: and in this Caſe alſo, the Life is much concern'd; for, if any Organ be out of order, it muſt be reduced by the Vital Principle, <hi>Anima:</hi> That Plaſtic Power which made all the Organic Parts; <hi>that</hi> only muſt mend them, with the help of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines promoting and aſſiſting.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60019:14"/>
            <p>All the Deſigns of Curing, are in aſſiſting the <hi>Governing</hi> Principle, to reſtore this or that Part defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; and in this Work, all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines operate firſt upon the <hi>Life.</hi> No <hi>Chirurgical</hi> Cure is rightly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned; no Application made to any Part; but it muſt operate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Life</hi> in that Part; elſe no healing, no ſtrengthening, no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if the Means be not proper and agreeable; Nature which is the Life, refuſing ſuch Helps, and not complying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; then no good Effect, can be expected from ſuch Endeavours: <hi>Invitâ Natura, irrita ſunt omnia.</hi> The Body is but paſſive, inferior, and inſtrumental; The Vital Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, is <hi>Dominus fac totum;</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding and governing this <hi>Body,</hi> ſubjected to its Will and Power; who formed all the <hi>Parts</hi> thereof; ſupports and maintains them in their Order and Offices; that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60019:15"/>moves all, and acts all <hi>ad nutum;</hi> at leaſt <hi>ad poſſe:</hi> The Carcaſs is but the <hi>Cortex</hi> or Shell; the Life is the Kernel. This is the Healing Principle, that cures and reſtores the Body, by the help of good Medicines. <hi>(Deus creavit medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam; qui nihil fruſtrâ fecit.)</hi> A true knowledge of the Vital Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in its governing power; with that of Medicines; are the two prime Acquirements to be ſought for by a Phyſician; to enable him in the Office of Curing.</p>
            <p>'Tis this Vital Principle, that diſtinguiſheth Bodies, by various Temperaments; <hi>Hot, Cold, Moist,</hi> and <hi>Dry:</hi> And diſtributeth to each <hi>Part,</hi> its proper and requiſite Temperature in their Formation; maintaining that due Tone after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; until changed by <hi>Age, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta genus,</hi> and <hi>Accidents:</hi> And this is performed, firſt upon the <hi>primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Spermatick</hi> Matter in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60019:15"/>Womb; afterwards by tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and modefying. Alimentary Supplies, in the whole courſe of Life: And as this Vital Principle <hi>(Seneſcit.)</hi> declines in Vigour and Vitallity; the temper of the whole, and every particular Part do change alſo.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Temperament</hi> of the Body, changeth eminently; as the Vital Principle alters in the Three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Stadiums of Human Life: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Childhood, Manhood, and old Age; the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of Vitality, aſcending and deſcending; which does not fall out ſo by Accident; but by the conſtant courſe of Human Nature: And how can this proceed? but from the mutability of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Life.</p>
            <p>Temperaments do not reſult <hi>(Ex mutua actione &amp; paſſione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariarum qualitatum elementorum.)</hi> from Qualities of Elementary Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60019:16"/>(according to common Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) but from the various ſtate and condition of the Vital Principle, which predominates over Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Matter, and Elementary Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: (ſubjugated under the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick Form.) That Principle which formed all the Organs; giving to each their due Temperament <hi>(ad juſtitium)</hi> having Semenal Matter under its Plaſtic Power, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of and modefy at will: Now alſo, and through the race of Man's Life, rules and ſupports the ſame; maintains ſuch Temperaments, as <hi>ſutable</hi> to its own deſignes and ſervice in Vital Actions. The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraments of viſible Organic Parts, ſhews the temper and diſtemper of the inviſible Life. And here by the way, you may take notice; that Febrile intemperate Heat, is but the Aeſtuation of the Vital Principle, offended and diſturbed by Morbific Cauſes; and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60019:16"/>as is ſet forth by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: But of this elſewhere more at large. <hi>Ignota Febris,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But I have met with an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis which ſtands in my way; oppoſing this Doctrine of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raments diametrically: <hi>That the Craſis of the Soul, follows the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament of the Body. (Cujus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium verum est)</hi> which is as much as to fay; The Cart draws the Horſe. I might take Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at the word <hi>Craſis;</hi> but 'ile paſs that by; and only examine the Import of the Sentence. This Aſſertion dethrones and deveſts the Governing Principle, of its Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Ruling. Power: And to ſay; the <hi>paſſive</hi> Body preſides over, leads, or alters the <hi>active</hi> Spirit; is <hi>contradictio in terminis:</hi> directly oppoſite to the Nature and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Agent and Patient. <hi>Omne Agens est actu; Patiens verò pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, Ax.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60019:17"/>
            <p>True it is; the Body, or Parts thereof, do not always yield obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to the Commands and Power of the Governing Vital Principle; as ſometimes by reaſon of their incapacity, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental unfitneſs, to perform their Offices: But they do not influence, or have any enticing, biaſſing, or coercive Power in their <hi>natural</hi> State; to diſpoſe or change the Vital Agent, to whom they are <hi>Vaſſals;</hi> and readily obey; ſave only their non-compliance in Duty with its ruling Energy, by their <hi>preternatural</hi> incapacity. As when the Organs are vitiated, unſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and unfit for Action; the Life grieves, pines, and is ſick more or leſs, as the Parts are in Office principal or inferior; and the Ability of the Vital Principle more or leſs capable to retrieve the Injury: And this may be obſerved in all Diſeaſes; how the <hi>Strength,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60019:17"/>Briskneſs, Complexion</hi> or Colour, Temperament or <hi>Habit</hi> of Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are changed more or leſs, as the Corporal Impediments are greater or leſs; But all theſe Alterations proceeding from <hi>male</hi> Affectedneſs, Condolence and Anguiſh of the Vital Principle, provoked thereto, and interrupted in regular Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by ſuch particular Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and not otherwiſe ſeduced, by following the Temperament of the Body; which is mutable at the pleaſure, and diſpleaſure of the Supream Ruling Power; as being ſubjected under that Domination and Soveraignity.</p>
            <p>Having ſhewed the <hi>Origin</hi> of Human Life by Generation; the <hi>Progreſs</hi> by Inſtability and Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I come now to inquire into the Cauſes of its <hi>Duration</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi> And here you may take notice, that every Species of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat Creatures have their ſeveral
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60019:18"/>Durations of Life, allotted for their natural Courſe, longer or ſhorter, according to, and from the different <hi>ſpecifick</hi> diſtinguiſhing Principles of their Life. <hi>Quod dat eſſe; dat breve, vel longam eſſe:</hi> The meaſure and extent of Human Life, is taken from the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of the Principle of Life, in the <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick</hi> Nature: But the Duration of <hi>Individuals,</hi> and their Term of Life; is not ſo certain and ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate with the <hi>Specifick;</hi> as being liable to various Accidents, and preternatural Cauſes of Abrevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Notwithſtanding, by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's appointment; Duration is repoſited in the Vital Principle.</p>
            <p>But there is an Opinion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Humidum radicale;</hi> a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple grounded in the Learned, both Philoſophers and Phyſicians; from whom it is become popular, and generally received: That there is a <hi>Radical</hi> oleaginous moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60019:18"/>in human Bodies; and this feeds the Life, as Oyl maintains Fire in the <hi>Lamp:</hi> which Oil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſumed, the Flame extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth: Semblably the Life ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, when Radical moiſture is waſted. This <hi>Analogy</hi> thus inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; does not carry any Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Reſemblance, and will not hold true: Either in comparing the <hi>Efficients</hi> or <hi>Agents;</hi> nor in their <hi>Matter</hi> upon which they work; nor their <hi>Manner</hi> of Action; nor in thier <hi>Ends,</hi> to which they tend: But in all theſe they differ much, and are not <hi>analogous.</hi> The two Agents, <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Human</hi> Vital Principle; are very diſſimilar in thier Natures: The one a <hi>Depraeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> that acts by conſuming; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>Reparator,</hi> that works by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing &amp; reſtoring. Secondly, they differ in the <hi>Matter</hi> upon which they operate: The firſt requiring <hi>olea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginous,</hi> fluid, and a peculiar <hi>ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60019:19"/>Matter: the other, <hi>Terrene, Aqueous, Saline,</hi> or ſulphureous mixt Subſtances, humid or dry of all ſorts, ſuch as our Food is, of various kinds, Meat and Drink. Thirdly, They differ and are diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milar in their <hi>manner</hi> of Action; the one violently preying upon, and devouring the (Pabulum) oily matter: The other operating upon its Object, deliberately and gently by <hi>Retexture;</hi> tranſmuting and tranſmitting; ſeparating <hi>(utile ab in utili)</hi> and diſtributing, to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Parts, for neceſſary and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Uſes. Fourthly, They dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in their <hi>Ends;</hi> the one termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates in <hi>waſting</hi> and <hi>conſuming:</hi> The other in <hi>repleniſhing,</hi> repairing and reſtoring Human Bodies; for noble ends and purpoſes; Health, Strength, and prolongation of Life. Thus we ſee; the Similitude (ſo intended) anſwers not in any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; does not illuſtrate the Life
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60019:19"/>of Man; but miſrepreſents, dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens it, is fruſtraneous and injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and no ſuch thing as, <hi>flamma Biolychnii;</hi> nor the Reſemblance.</p>
            <p>This learned Fiction, if I may ſo call it; (againſt the Judgment of ſo many <hi>Sages</hi>) and I can give it no better Title; becauſe it hath no Foundation, nor <hi>Being</hi> in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature. I grant there is a <hi>Humidum primigenium;</hi> an origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Moiſture in that Seminal Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of which the Embryo is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neated and formed; but this Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus is ſoon changed, exhauſted and ſpent; being transformed by the <hi>Architectonic</hi> Spirit into different kinds of Spermatick Parts; <hi>Bones, Cartilages, Ligaments,</hi> &amp;c. the which, and afterwards all <hi>ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> Parts alſo; are maintained by adventitious Supplies from Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, not by a Radical Stock. And this advenient nutritious Juice daily extracted from Food, is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muted
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60019:20"/>and fitted continually for every Part; by the <hi>Occonomic</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Principle, which was the Formative Principle: So that there is no need of <hi>Radical</hi> Moiſture; the Stomach is the <hi>Conduit</hi> from whence all Parts, adjacent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, are irrigated and ſupplied with convenient Moiſture: And ſince there is no <hi>Radical</hi> antique <hi>Primigeneous</hi> Moiſture; ſo there is no want thereof; Nature having provided a freſh Spring, more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing and enlivening, than any ſtale Liquor of ancient ſtanding. The Vital Principle, ſo long as it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues vigorous in the <hi>Ventricle;</hi> will not let the Body want a Supplement of proper and laudable Moiſture, from this Fountain that feeds all the Vital Streams.</p>
            <p>Thus you may plainly ſee; the Notion of <hi>humidum radicale,</hi> to be a falſe Conception; in that ſenſe, and for ſuch uſe, as the world is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60019:20"/>made to believe; that the Life ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſheth by the exhauſtion of <hi>Radical</hi> Moiſture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Multa alia problemata &amp; paradoxa</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>ex praeceſſis tractanda, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidò ſurgunt: ſed quò plura hîc af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feram; eò etiam plura afferenda ſe offerent; quapropter, (impreſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum) aliò calamum divertere lubet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to reduce all our Diſcourſe, and make it ſerviceable in Practice; and to let you know theſe are not empty Notions and unprofitable; but of great moment in Phyſick: Here you may learn <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Admonition; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; to know the more noble and better Part of Man.</p>
            <p>'Tis this Vital Luminary <hi>(Sol Microceſmi)</hi> that vivifies the Earthen lump of Human Body; and makes it a living <hi>Automaton:</hi> And by whoſe irradiating influence through the Regions and Parts of this <hi>Orb;</hi> all the various Motions, Mutations
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60019:21"/>and Ceſſations <hi>(efficienter aut pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vativé)</hi> do moſtly depend.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Plaſtic</hi> Principle inſpired <hi>(derivativè)</hi> from that Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration into the <hi>Protoplaſt;</hi> draws the firſt Lineaments of Human Fabrick; forms and finiſheth all the interior Parts thereof; for <hi>Magnitude, Figure, Poſition, Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Connexion,</hi> and <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> moſt requiſite to exert and diſplay, all the various Faculties of Human Nature.</p>
            <p>But here by the way, I muſt take notice; that ſome melancholy <hi>Phanſies</hi> (and to correſpond with the Opinion of Souls daily created Origin) have <hi>rhetorically,</hi> but unſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably; termed the Body a Priſon; a toyling Work-houſe; and the Grave of the Soul: But I muſt think otherwiſe; not a <hi>Priſon,</hi> but a <hi>Pallace;</hi> excelling Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks (<hi>Galen</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) for Magnificence, Uſe, Convenience,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60019:21"/>and Delight, moſt accommodate, and connatural with the Principle of Life. Not an <hi>Ergaſtulum;</hi> but a Chariot of Pleaſure. Not <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum,</hi> but a living Monument; the Mirrour of the Terreſtrial Globe; <hi>è luto ſinctum:</hi> And therefore what happens to diſcompoſe this Auguſt <hi>Pavilion</hi> to interrupt the Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and Felicity therein; is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental and preternatural; admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing us the mutability of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man State. And <hi>if</hi> this <hi>opifice</hi> be fo admirable; the <hi>opifex</hi> much more: <hi>propter quod unumquodque eſt tale; illud eſt magis tale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This dextrous Limner, draws not the <hi>Effigies</hi> and Reſemblance; but makes the <hi>living</hi> Man: Delineates, Shapes, and Sizeth all Bodies with peculiar <hi>imparity</hi> of Dimenſions; and joins therewith by Coextenſion: Puts a diſtinguiſhing Figure upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Face: Prepares and tempers E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemental Matter into various <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions:</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60019:22"/>Preſents Man in all the different Aſpects; <hi>Smiling, Lowr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Bold, Drooping, Fierce, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Ruling Principle acts all the unruly Paſſions; of <hi>Fear, Love, Hatred, Anger,</hi> &amp;c. And by its Ubiquitary Vital Preſence in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Body; does determine upon all ſenſible Objects, with Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, or Diſplacence. Alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſifies individual Natures: by peculiar <hi>Proprieties, Temperaments, Inclinations, Averſations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Rational Principle, keeps the Stores of <hi>Intellectual</hi> Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and puts a diſtinguiſhing Character upon Man, from all his fellow Creatures: And alſo makes a particular diſtinction amongſt Men; by a different proportion and meaſure, of <hi>Ingeny, Subtility, Sagacity, Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Memory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis this Regent Principle that governs all the Members of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60019:22"/>Body; moves, directs, ſupports, enables them in their Duties; and keeps them in the due order of their ſubordinate Offices: this is the internal, efficient Agent, and ſupream Moderator of all Human Actions; <hi>Natural, Vital,</hi> and <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal,</hi> ſo diſtinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Microcoſmical</hi> Luminary <hi>orient;</hi> makes the blooming Spring of Youth: from thence arriving to the <hi>Meridian</hi> Heighth; the Strength and State of Manhood: And from thence declining; the withering <hi>Autumn;</hi> and then the unpleaſant Winter of old <hi>Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Vital Luminary <hi>ſerene</hi> in Government; makes the chearful State of <hi>Health:</hi> This <hi>clouded</hi> and impedited, in its Regent <hi>Aſtral</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux, by diſcompoſure and defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Members in this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; then ariſeth the ſad gloomy State of <hi>Sickneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>From hence the <hi>Apoplectic</hi> Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</item>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60019:23"/>
               <item>The <hi>Paralitic</hi> deſertions of Vital Influx.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Convulſive</hi> Struglings of the Life.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hyſteric</hi> Suffocating Damps.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Febrile</hi> Scorchings of the incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Vital Spirit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humoral</hi> Fermenting Flouds; and Conſumptive Ebbs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hydropic</hi> Inundations.</item>
               <item>Stormy <hi>Aguiſh</hi> Concuſſions of the <hi>Microcoſme.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Flatulent Rumblings, and Cavernous Belchings.</item>
               <item>Exhauſting Tranſpirations.</item>
               <item>The impetuous Fluxes, of the expelling Vital Agent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Thus acting all the <hi>Comic</hi> and <hi>Tragic</hi> Viciſſitudes in Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: And what not, acted or committed in the little World of Man; that this Vital Principle, is not the <hi>principal</hi> Actor therein; or chiefeſt Sufferer thereby? Cauſes <hi>material</hi> and <hi>occaſianal,</hi> provoking the Life to <hi>enormous</hi> Motions; or
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60019:23"/>impediting <hi>Vital</hi> Influence; are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and too many here be enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merated.</p>
            <p>As this Vital Principle acts the <hi>Chiefeſt</hi> Part in all Diſeafes: So likewiſe it performs principally and efficiently, the Cures of all Diſeaſes; and otherwiſe the Body cannot be Cured. <hi>Natura corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borata eſt Morborum meditacrix.</hi> Helmont.</p>
            <p>As this is the Curing Principle; this alſo is the Principle firſt to be Cured: Comforted and Refreſhed in the times of weakneſs; allevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, when oppreſſed; allayed and eaſed from <hi>Pains:</hi> reduced out of Frets and Paſſions; cauſed by <hi>Organic</hi> Impediments diſordering the <hi>Oeconony;</hi> or from external In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries: And they that deſign Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring otherwiſe, aim not aright; but proſecute by falſe ſteps, and their Endeavours Fruſtraneous.</p>
            <p>'Tis this <hi>Vital</hi> Principle, that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60019:24"/>muſt firſt be ſtrengthned; and the Body can receive no <hi>Strength,</hi> but from thence. In this Vital Power, lies the <hi>Strength</hi> of Human Nature; and in this ſame, lies the <hi>Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and weakneſs of Nature: This ſets Man up; and this lets him fall down.</p>
            <p>'Tis this Principle, that receives the firſt Refreſhment and Aſſiſtance by Food; then communicates, and fits it for the Body: After the ſame manner it does with Phyſick. This <hi>Healing</hi> Principle, diſtinguiſheth and cloſeth amicably with proper good Medicines; directs and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits their Virtue to this or that Diſeaſed Part, wanting Relief. All the deſigns of Curing centers here; in diſpoſing and aſſiſting of the Life, to repair decaying and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective Organs.</p>
            <p>This Vital Principle the Organ <hi>maker,</hi> and <hi>Organiſt;</hi> muſt be the Organ <hi>mender;</hi> and otherwiſe not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60019:24"/>to be done: Medicines are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to work with, managed by the Life; which if proper, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocuous, powerful, and duly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited, they give Aid, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce good Effects: But if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; they prove ineffectual at beſt; more often injurious; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times mortal. And how efficacious good Medicines are to be deſigned, ſuting with, and eſtabliſhing the <hi>Oeconomy;</hi> I have elſewhere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: <hi>(The Practice of Phyſick duly Regulated)</hi> to promote ſuch Operations, as Nature (the Life) is defective in, and wants aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to perform: which Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being proſecuted with well tried Medicines compleatly adapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereto; do anſwer every <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> in all Diſeaſes, and Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Caſes.</p>
            <p>But as for <hi>ex tempore</hi> preſcribed Recipe's, <hi>pro re nata;</hi> excogitated new untried Compoſitions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60019:25"/>to <hi>Shop</hi> preparation; I can never be reconciled to that Mode of Practice, and Novel Invention; until I ſhall looſe half my Reaſon, and ſome of my Senſes: And how the World came to be <hi>trapan'd</hi> out of their Judgments; deeming it a learned and ſafe Contrivance; is to me a great wonder; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither true Learning, nor Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therein to <hi>Patients</hi> or <hi>Profeſſors;</hi> as evidently appears in that Sheet named (not yet anſwered <hi>Ne Gry Quidem</hi>) and bids defiance to the Vanity of Preſcribing; which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd departure from the laudable and learned Induſtry of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients;</hi> hath fill'd the World with <hi>thouſands</hi> of frivolous, and mean Medicines; and hath raiſed a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying Generation of <hi>Quacks,</hi> to Practice therewith: which cauſed a learned <hi>Author</hi> to complain: <hi>Sed hoc ſaltem ſilentio non tranſmitten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum exiſtimamus; peſſimè illos de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60019:25"/>publico meritos, qui primi hanc ſummè arduam arma medica conficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di diſciplinam, à medicina avulſerunt; &amp; ſervis ſuis unicè Commiſerunt: merâ ignaviâ, &amp; malè Suada Animi elatione,</hi> &amp;c. ſo he goes on ſharply Reproving. <hi>Chr. Langius. Curioſ. Medic.</hi> p. 146.</p>
            <p>I challenge any learned Man, and all the Preſcribers in this <hi>Mode;</hi> to make out this Practice <hi>Rational, Learned, Safe,</hi> and <hi>Hopeful:</hi> On the contrary part, (if not yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed) I will farther prove this Preſcribing Invention, an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Formality; a blind <hi>hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous</hi> Adventure; a <hi>Remora</hi> to the Progreſs and Advancement of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; wherein the Lives of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,</hi> and Reputation of <hi>Phyſitians</hi> are unſafe; but Eaſe and Gain ſmothers all the Injuries at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> not ſeeing, or not regarding the impending Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60019:26"/>
            <p>And here I might Remark at large; How eaſie it is to impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and blind the <hi>credulous</hi> World; with the erroneous Seductions, and biaſſed Intereſts, of learned Men: But of this (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) I have ſaid enough; perhaps too much; <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas odium parit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the preceding Diſcourſe; you may take notice, and not think it ſtrange Doctrine; that I have made the general diviſion of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, into Spirital and Corporal (in the <hi>Tract</hi> following) much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the common received Learning; of <hi>Similar, Organical,</hi> and <hi>Common;</hi> which for good Reaſons rejected; as you may ſee hereafter; <hi>(Inquiries into the general Catalogue of Diſeaſes)</hi> where by Spirital Diſeaſes, not meaning Diſeaſes of the Animal or Vital Spirits; but of the Vital Principle, or Governing Spirit; which is the chief Agent, and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60019:26"/>in all Sickneſs. And as I ſhall have time to proſecute there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; you will have a much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent account of particular Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, than as yet ſet forth.</p>
            <p>The Body <hi>(Animae domicilium)</hi> is a meer paſſive Principle; as void of ſenſe or motion, as a Houſe, abſtractly conſidered from the Life, or vital internal Agent: and although Corporal Organic Knowledge by Anatomy, is good and requiſite; yet a true account of the Oeconomy; the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Governing Principle; the manner of diſpenſing its Vital Power towards the ſubjected Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; is more ſublime; and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be traced, ſo far as the light of Reaſon, by true Obſervations will conduct us. But after all the continued Anatomic Diſquiſitions, the Vital Oeconomy hath been but deficiently and obſcurely ſet forth; as the Notion of Diſeaſes in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60019:27"/>and the account of Diſeaſes in particular, by their Cauſes erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly aſſigned, do evidence in many, or moſt of them; which miſtakes have happened from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Knowledge in the Vital Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Power.</p>
            <p>This Vital Principle, being the principal Actor in all the Scenes of Human Life; is firſt and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſought and traced; ſince the Dependants from thence are ſo many and great in Human Nature; both in the State of <hi>Health,</hi> as alſo in <hi>Sickneſs;</hi> in regular Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and alſo in preternatural Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>This is the chief and main Pillar that ſupports Humanity.</p>
            <p>From whoſe <hi>Stability</hi> and <hi>Inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; Firmneſs</hi> and <hi>Infirmity; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity,</hi> and warping from <hi>Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> moſtly depends the various Viciſſitudes and Alterations in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Government; whoſe <hi>Vigour</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60019:27"/>and <hi>Durability,</hi> maintains the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>duration</hi> of Man's Body in the whole Courſe of Life.</p>
            <p>This is the Reſtoring and Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Principle of Bodily decays and corrupt waſting: And this is the <hi>Principle</hi> to be reſtored and robo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, in weakneſs and a declining State.</p>
            <p>This is the maintaining <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> of <hi>Health;</hi> and this is the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſuffering <hi>Principle</hi> in <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> and a dying ſtate; from hence the ſighs, the groans, and pangs: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Vitality,</hi> hangs <hi>Mortality;</hi> the Principle of Life, the Object and Aim of Death.</p>
            <p>This is the Vital <hi>Principle</hi> that receives Aſſiſtance, Refreſhment and Roboration <hi>(primariò)</hi> from <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Phyſick;</hi> from glad <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,</hi> and good <hi>Company;</hi> from wholſome <hi>Air,</hi> and pleaſant <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects;</hi> from <hi>Exerciſe</hi> and <hi>Rest;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60019:28"/>Sleep</hi> and <hi>Waking:</hi> And from the the ſame Principle <hi>(Secundariò &amp; participativè)</hi> Bodily Refection, Convaleſcence, and Thriving is communicated.</p>
            <p>Herein lies the Knowledge of Human Nature; this Governing Principle diſpoſing, moving and enabling all Bodily Members, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form in all the Actions appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Human Life: whatever is act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or done in the Body, or by the Body outward; is performed <hi>(ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficienter)</hi> by the Virtue and Power of this Vital Principle: It is then very rational to accuſe, and charge this Soveraign <hi>Agent</hi> with defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, irregularity and inability ſometimes; being liable to altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and decay, from lapſed, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Nature. But the common Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and generally received Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, runs upon another <hi>Bias;</hi> and aſcribes all the Defects and Diſeaſes of Human Nature to the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60019:28"/>
               <hi>paſſive</hi> governed Principle; and makes all the <hi>Morbous</hi> Alterations and Decays, to ariſe from <hi>Humoral</hi> and <hi>Organic</hi> Impediments: which Doctrine muſt needs be unſound; if our preceding Diſcourſe be true; and profound <hi>Helmont,</hi> much out of the way, where he aſſerts; <hi>in pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto vita ſubjectum inhaeſionis morbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the preceding Doctrine there ariſeth theſe following Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms. Theorical and Practical, as the reſult of this Work.</p>
            <p>That the vital Principle is the <hi>Spring</hi> from whence flows all the various Actions of Mans Life, both internal and external; which <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> contains the knowledge of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature.</p>
            <p>It much behoves every Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, to have a true perception of this ruling comprehenſive Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: To know its <hi>Riſe, Race,</hi> and <hi>Period:</hi> The <hi>Architectonick</hi> power,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60019:29"/>and <hi>Monarchical</hi> Domination in the Microcoſm.</p>
            <p>To diſtinguiſh the regular, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid and ſerene ſtate of this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Principle; from the <hi>enormous,</hi> irregular, and preternatural moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>To diſcern the vigorous <hi>aſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and drooping <hi>declenſions</hi> of this vital power, in the courſe of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life.</p>
            <p>To underſtand the <hi>Central</hi> Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and Royal Seat of Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Government.</p>
            <p>To know the irradiatating vital Influence; and <hi>Ecliptick</hi> Interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>To diſcern the Signals of Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual <hi>Stability, Inſtability,</hi> and <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rability</hi> of this Regal Power; by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Actions, and diſtinguiſhing cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Fabrick.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> tend to the Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Subverſion of Vital Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And all the deſigns of <hi>Curing,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60019:29"/>are rightly directed and guided by the method and courſe of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: For reducing the Ruling Power, when <hi>Enormous;</hi> in aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when <hi>defective</hi> or diſabled; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo where, and how impedited by diſorder of the ſubjected Members.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> take their Riſe more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from a defection and inſtability of the Vital Governing <hi>Principle;</hi> than from the decays of the <hi>Body,</hi> by Age or Accidents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Organic</hi> and Humoral Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, provoke the Vital <hi>Principle</hi> to Paſſion and Enormity; thereby raiſing the Storms and Tempeſts of acute and ſharp Diſeaſes, diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole <hi>oeconomy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All ſcorching <hi>Inflamations,</hi> and preternatural <hi>febrile</hi> Heats; ariſe from the fiery Paſſions, and aeſtua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Perturbation of the Vital Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</p>
            <p>All <hi>ſtony</hi> Concretions in Human Bodies, proceed from a depraved
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60019:30"/>
               <hi>petrefying</hi> diſpoſition of the Vital Tranſmuting Power, not from any Humoral <hi>Elementary</hi> Matter.</p>
            <p>Impreſſions of <hi>Cold</hi> are firſt made upon the <hi>Life;</hi> afterwards produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Bodily Effects: <hi>Hoarfneſs, Flegm, Coughing, Rheums,</hi> ſtiffneſs of <hi>Limbs,</hi> &amp;c. theſe are ſignals of the Life aſſaulted and male-affected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pains</hi> in any part of the Body, Heart Sickneſs, Fainting, Nauſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Loathing of Food; are the ſufferings and complaints of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Principle</hi> oppreſſed and grieved.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Contuſions</hi> and <hi>Wounds</hi> made in the Body, are aſſaults and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in upon the Life: which the Vital <hi>Principle (efficienter)</hi> muſt repair and reſtore; by the help and aſſiſtance of Art, if remedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Corporal Excreſcences, <hi>Wens, Warts, Puſtuls, Tumors,</hi> &amp;c. are the effects of depraved Tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Alimentary <hi>ſuccus</hi> in one,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60019:30"/>or more of the digeſtive Offices; the Vital Principle unſtable and ſwerving from rectitude; or unable to withſtand and overcome the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries offered, by an evil <hi>Dietetick Regimen;</hi> and labouring under ſuch ill circumſtances of ſome of the ſix Non-naturals; ſo termed by Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians.</p>
            <p>All Corporal Decays and Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ariſing by Age or common due wearing and uſage; are the deficiency and gradual declenſions of the Vital <hi>Principle,</hi> abating and withering in Vigour and Vitality; tending to, and portending the <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod</hi> of Vital Government.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 27. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
